Security in fact a software bill of
materials wouldn't it be great if you
had a list of all the dependencies in
your software so that as a security team
you could go through it and you could
know exactly where you stand and you
didn't have to go out and Trace down all
the dependencies and pull them down from
their different places um recently after
I
did a video about go mod
vendor uh which as you probably know
creates a vendor directory inside of
your go project that pulls down all of
the Essential Software that is that that
go project depends upon which means that
it actually brings down the non-test
files any of the.go files are brought
down the readme the license and some
stuff like that it puts it in a
directory called vendor I've done a
separate video about this but I've I've
been kind of turned on to this idea in
fact I do it everywhere now there are
lots of reasons there's another video
about the five ways to use private uh
repos in your cicd for when you're doing
go builds and then there's another video
a 61 on go mod vendor about how that
solves that entire problem by not having
your module have any external
dependencies whatsoever they're all
internal and after I made that video
somebody a security person came to me
and said hey have you did you know about
this software this software bill of
materials and thebomb from sisa and I
was like no what's that so the American
cyber Defense Agency which is actually a
really cool place to work uh if you ever
wanted to work there this is not an
advertisement for the cyber security
Defense Agency um but if you are okay
you know get giving up your life
essentially to the government having
them know every every single little
thing about you and you're an American
and you want to get access to
technologies that you cannot use legally
any other
way the American cyber cyber Defense
Agency is one of the places that would
be really great to work um the national
coordinator for critical infrastructure
security and resilience uh otherwise
known as sisa critical infrastructure
security and resilience so um there was
actually recently uh before we get into
this there was recently a um I mean
y'all know I've been in security for
long long time uh unofficially I mean
I've been doing security things um
security compliance audit software and
all of that kind of thing uh I've been
hacked I've hacked so I'm interested in
security I'm if you had to pick me i'
probably more of a gray hat than
anything but um I mean the great Jedi
the great Jedi right great Jedi they're
the cool Jedi so so why would any of
this have anything to do with that well
whenever you're writing software you
want to be sure that you don't add a
vulnerability and if you want to look up
the biggest vulnerability and as far as
I'm concerned the biggest one ever there
was a worm and I I can't even remember
the name now there was there have been
more than one there's been more than one
major worm which is when somebody puts
software into a dependency and that
makes it into software and then that
software gets deployed to the world um
the XY compression algorithm that was
going to go into SSH actually um that
that was also the same sort of system
was like a dependency and if you read
the the history on that one they were um
actually attacking the the the
maintainer of that project it's
absolutely fascinating there's a right
up I think it's unwired about that um
but again what does this have to do with
go mod vender um well in every one of
those cases um whether the person's
overworked or whatever uh it wouldn't
matter as much because they would you
would have a local you know bill of
materials that's what the bomb is for uh
you'd have a local bill of materials
that talks about all your dependencies
that would be uh present and accounted
for so um let me let's go through and
read this and then I'll I'll make my
conclusion here so the software build
materials has emerged as a key building
block in software security and software
supply chain risk
management so I don't think I need to
tell you that the Enterprise and as and
everybody else needs to focus on
security more right supply chain what is
a supply chain if you're new this
terminology supply chain is every single
thing all the systems that that exist
that get you what you need from one from
point A to point B to give you an idea
of this when I worked on the Nike ID
project um the supply chain was the
biggest challenge because you know
somebody could go into uh a website and
Order up uh a name or something and it
would pop up on it would show up on
their on their shoot and it was a supply
chain nightmare because you know they
would have to change one piece at one
point and then that would have to be
communicated and would have to be
filtered down the other term the other
place that people hear supply chain all
the time is the lack of electronics over
the last couple years because of the
backup um from covid and electronics not
being available uh another very very
very popular supply chain attack um uh
well a story about it was when and there
is still debate about whether this even
happened uh this was actually a
Bloomberg article uh and I'll just refer
to it there was um uh it was one of the
biggest hacks in history and it was a
supply chain issue where allegedly um
video cards were were taken and then
there was a chip placed on the video
card and um when the chip was placed on
the video card in other words the
allegedly in China uh the the producers
of these Electronics were not aware and
they were unpack packaged and then the
chip was placed on the video card and
the GPU and then they were repackaged
and they were shipped off to the states
and allegedly these things landed inside
of Amazon servers and you can go read um
uh the the Bloomberg article about that
let me let me go actually this is this
is um Bloomberg let's see if I can find
it um uh uh supply chain hack and I'm I
wasn't going to tiny chips were
allegedly here we go
um blueberg be the big hack here here it
is okay
so again this is just to draw a
comparison the big hack how China used
the tiny chip to infiltrate us companies
uh making a video my wife just walked in
um all right so here we go Amazon being
kind of quietly about any startup blah
blah blah so this is actually extremely
um controversial the point the point is
is that the supply chain in other words
all of the vendors along the way that
provide a thing uh are targets and any
point in the supply chain along the way
can be a Target right it can be attacked
it can be uh taken out right well how
what does this have to do with software
so the software supply chain to go back
to read um the terminology here uh the
software build Matas has moved as a
software supply chain risk management
thing so software has the same problem
because software can be you know there's
multiple dependencies you have this
project who has a dependency on this
other project and this has a and they
all live all over the place right um and
depending on how the the software I mean
if you look at npm no package manager
and how it was created I mean you I I
don't want to go there but at one point
you had to like send like a personal
email to Isaac Schuler to get your
dependency made and there was no
validation whatsoever and you were boom
you were in and and and there are things
like which the Abomination which is jsx
which actually runs software from you
know an external with multiple external
dependencies without on your machine
without even validating any of it and
just to give you a sense of the
comparison there was no check some
evaluation to tell whether you were even
the actual software there was no m in
the middle of ATT check there was
nothing so there's million ways you
could attack the software supply chain
in those cases you would like go after
the the software that was getting pulled
down right and and in any way whether
you and in I think the biggest wor of
all they actually were able to take over
one of the accounts and publish uh a
malign you know Trojan version of a
package and then that package then got
built into everything else and then that
that then affected every single project
that used that dependency okay so so
that that's the attack Vector if you're
going to attack a system um you're going
to look for for it's the software supply
chain and the hardware supply chain and
you're going to find a weakness in there
and you're going to attack it you're
either going to pretend to be that
person or you're going to get some
overwork engineer to to put your changes
in over time which is how they got the X
Y thing in or you're just going to
inject your stuff in the middle of it on
the network so that so that your stuff
gets downloaded instead of the other
stuff that's a man in the middle of
attack all of these things that I just
talked about are like you know
kindergarten level basic security
considerations for somebody who actually
works in security right so again what
does this have to do with go mod vendor
and the software Bild materials so the
supply chain that's being attacked one
of the ways to prevent uh or to know
that you're being attacked or not really
to prevent but to know is to be able to
keep a record of this stuff an sbom is a
nested inventory a list of ingredients
that make up software components
so this is the list that you want this
is where all the things are being made
while not a Brand New Concept the ideas
and implementations have advanced since
2018 through a number of collaborative
efforts including National
telecommunications information and
administration sisa is advancing the
esom adoption of practice by
facilitating community-led work with a
focus on scaling and operation and
operationalization big word there as
well as tools new technologies and new
use cases this website will also be an
ex for the broader set of sbom resource
across digital ecosystem around the
world an sbom related concept is the
vulnerability exploitation exchange
exploitability a Vex document is an
attestation a form of security advisory
that indicates whether a product or
products are affected by noal
abilities um so if you if you ask me
right there I think this is just fancy
speak for stuff that's kind of already
in existence um I could be wrong so
obviously ly you know I'm pretty new to
this uh to the es bomb thing so let me
know we do have like you
know nationally renowned cyber security
architects in our community some of whom
may Cham chime in a little bit it might
be early for some of them um who have
actually participated in some of this um
you know including Consulting with the
upper levels of government um about how
to do this stuff but at the end of the
day it sounds like you know like how
GitHub will like give you a report on
all your
vulnerabilities well that's kind of the
sort of thing I think that was that's
what a Vex document would actually be um
sisa also advances the sbom work by
facilitating Community engagement to
advance and refine sbom coordinating
with International industry inter agency
partners about esom imputations and
promoting uh esom as a transparency tool
across broader ecosystem US government
and the world if you has questions
please blah so so this seems to me like
it's a they're trying to come up with
some standardization across the board
across all software um and this is where
go mod vendor comes in because some
applications already do this right um
and let's let's let's pick on c for a
while for a bit right and everybody
loves to pick on C especially Russ
people but C is just a language right
it's a language that was created to
recreate Unix they didn't really think
about you know how are we going to
itemize all the dependencies and stuff
now they they have that and there are
many that do this now but they're they
were added after the fact and I'm I'm
not acquainted with that um you know
ecosystem of tools but but you know I'm
in terms of like running go mod vendor
or looking at a go check some file which
I'm sure you guys have seen um you know
when when even if you have like a uh
even when you have like here let's take
my little my little thing my little
theal thing that I've been doing if you
do you know the idea of having a a go do
some file that has all your dependencies
and the check some for that specific
dependency that specific package um is
not something that comes with C it's
kind of packed on here we have the you
know the actual list of the requirements
and over here we have the vendor
directory which contains my vendored
code as you can see there's no
underscore test in there and you know
you need to understand how how that
works something I think is interesting
here too is is that go PKG EML V3 three
this uses the this uses this creates a
directory structure that matches the um
that specifically matches the path from
the module uh and not necessarily the
source code so the source code for go go
package.
in3 is actually in uh go Das yaml uh
yaml that is the GitHub repo for this U
I can show you you can clone clone uh go
PKG let's see yaml yaml
and we see here that we are in the yaml
project and you can see that um oops
see well let's see we can cancel this
one right now so find
vendor I me let's compare the list here
so you can see here we got like dec. go
and over here we have deco. go but we
don't have this here so again that's
just a reminder of what is done you'll
see the license read me the notice is
copied over so those things are all
brought over um and the equivalent um of
a the equivalent of of an s bomb here I
mean so I assume that they're working on
coming up with an sbom that kind of
takes it kind of itemizes or comes up
with ways to itemize the dependencies
inside of a software package uh for
everything not just
for um you know one particular way but
what I'm trying to demonstrate here is
that go first of all go already does
this by by putting everything in the go
mod file including the exact version it
was used and the check sum uh which can
be used to validate that software and
and that is not turned off hey how are
you uh we're making YouTube video here
about
security um and so if you look at that
you can you can see so you already get
to feel you know happier about about
this let me let me show you one other
thing so
so you know let's just let's just let's
just cut to the chase here so what makes
you as a security person feel better
having uh having you know all those
dependencies listed in a single file
with the check
sums and then having the people building
that software if you were auditing which
one would which one would you find
easier to use this is where this
question is really coming from okay
which of the following would be easier
for you to deal with as a security
auditor right and I'm going to paint two
scenarios one of them is you come into
the software project and and you you
look at this
here and you're like okay I'm going to
go look at go dood actually let's let's
give you a good one I'm gonna pick on
one I'm gonna pick I'm gonna pick on
kubernetes which is disastrously bad
uh yeah I cannot help
myself let me see if I can find it again
um yeah I was actually I did a video
about this earlier the kubernetes
project is just this just so bad prise
okay again okay so pretend you're a
security auditor okay um you're a
security order you're like okay I need
I'm want to follow sbom I want to figure
out what things are safe uh what things
can I look at you know how do I know all
of this system dependencies well if it's
go you might not know it's go if it's a
security auditor you're not expect you
know every single language out there
right so I mean but but maybe you at
least have some casual sense of go so
you go in here and you say okay well
let's look at go mod file and it's oh
okay well this has got okay so it's
using an old version of go an old
extremely insecure version of go which
already that's a plag right this isn't
even a patch level this isn't this is
just like so we're not going to go there
secondly we're going to say okay well
what requirements does it have I mean if
I want to if I want to create an sbom
document let's let's assume that the
sbom uh standard has emerged and that I
mean as Government stuff goes they
usually end up coming up with some
standard way to put it even though it's
not particularly useful and then you you
end up having to like take whatever your
project is and then create a another
document out of the other out of that
document right so I'm not saying that's
what's going to happen with sbom but I
assume that's the kind of kind of thing
that's going to come out of it and that
means you're going to have to take a
thing and convert it over right so so
here we have the go require file I mean
the require setting that's all the
dependencies for this project on
everything else so that's the beginning
of that list right
except there's other dependencies here
that are not here now For Better or
Worse there are two dependencies
here on external projects which are
not really publicly shown and they got
the some again once again they got the
check some files here for these public
these things um and then but see if you
look at the go yo file the V3 file you
see that this package is a fork of the
go yaml library and is intended solely
for the consumption of the kubernetes
project this B this is a fork of blah
blah blah right so what they've done is
they've vendored this even though they
didn't use go mod vendor which I
complain about in another video so this
this is another project go yam
V3 is another project so there's a
dependency on that but as an auditor
this is kind of interesting as as an
auditor it makes it much easier for me
because I can now look at the source
code that's there I don't have to go
pull it down now even though as a go
developer I'd be kind of confused like
why are you not putting that all in the
vendor
directory you know that I still have the
software there so as an auditor the very
simply the very simple point I'm trying
to make as an auditor it's much easier
to have the list of all the dependencies
and and also a copy of all the relevant
code from those dependencies available
in the project snapshotted at a specific
version with check sums that prove that
that is the actual version that was
listed in the dependencies that is what
go mod vendor does the alternative to
that is to have just the list of
dependencies and a list of check sums
but to not actually validate where that
software is coming from so so in order
for you to understand this we have to
kind of Replay what it means to build
software and go and I'll try to keep
that simple but right now when you do go
build or go install or go get I me I
mean go get is implied in all of them
what happens is you go get and if
assuming it's all dependencies is on
public stuff it's private it's a pain in
the butt and I've made videos about that
but if it's public if it's public then
what does it do
go goes out to the check some the the
publicly available checkm cach servers I
think there go pg. I think those are the
ones and it checks to see if the version
it goes It goes and gets a cached
compiled version of the dependency and
downloads it it downloads the source
code for that and it I believe it
downloads the binary as well and it goes
to a caching server there Google uh
maintains a number of publicly available
caching servers and and those caching
services are are locked down and they're
depended on they're by all the go
projects that build anything public and
that brings down the thing it brings
down the check sum that's declared by
the project and that check sum is then
checked after that that cached compiled
thing is downloaded whether it it
compiles it on the fly or downloads the
binary I'm pretty sure it downloads the
binary but it Downs the binary uh that
is eventually going to get statically
linked into the final project and it
sticks that into your caching server
which is in your go directory wherever
that is and and then it you know it
makes sure that it still matches the
check some so it's doing everything that
you should do if you down download
something from the internet if you
download anything from the internet you
should download it and you should check
it against the checks to make sure
nothing happened in the download process
the man in the- Middle attack so so go
by default and by the way it has always
done this it's never been subjected to
man in the middle of attack because it's
always at least in the module system has
always done this it's always downloaded
and check these things against the check
some because they care about Security in
fact recently they've even um made
additions to make it so that uh the same
binary will always compile in the same
way so that you have binary
compatibility depending on so that you
can actually ensure that um if if if the
signature of the binary changes at all
that there's been some some tampering
going on and that's probably a good idea
because go is extremely popular with
hackers there's an article uh 4,000%
increase in go popularity 30 uh two
years ago uh by hackers because they can
take the same exact C code or whatever
they can offis uh the footprint of the
binary and recompile it um any code AS
go uh even though Rob P Pike has
explicitly said please don't write
malware with go it actually turns out to
be really really good for malware and
for that reason you're starting to see
lots and lots of packages written in and
go so being able to identify it as a big
thing um that also means that that you
know hacker know how go works and they
know how to attack the software supply
chain in this case the dependency trees
that come into uh the final project
right so as you can see so so let's
think about if you're a hacker what are
you going to attack right you could
attack the M the middle network midle
connection you can attack the software
caching servers which is how the worms
of the mpm were done um you can attack
the people who write the source code
that gets put into the caching servers
so that it bypasses all that you can't
attack that um and but and or you can of
course you could attack the actual repo
itself where the software is if you have
access to that um those are all the
places you could attack but when it
comes to auditing so so so what happens
if there is a security breach and this
is where go mod vender really really
really really shines I said three relies
on purpose okay imagine this scenario so
you're a security auditor right and
there is a critical I don't know how but
a critical vulnerability makes it into a
dependency of your project okay so let's
pick on I don't know let's pck on yaml
B3 right so yaml B3 which is used by
literally tens of thousands of projects
probably at this point let's say yaml V3
gets compromised and it actually makes
it all the way into the caching
server which not the caching server but
makes it into the um no that's right the
the the proxy server the centralized
servers that are that that contain the
checks and everything so so a a
vulnerable version of goo and there
isn't there isn't a vulnerability I'm
just saying this because this is this is
a big one right makes it all the way up
to the top and it is loaded it is
available for everybody and and you
don't get affected by it until you
rebuild right so let's say let's say
that vulnerability makes it out and it
lives it's it lives out there for let's
say a week right and anybody who's built
the project their project in the last
week who has updated their they'd have
to do two things to be vulnerable number
one they would have had to have updated
their dependencies without checking the
source code which happens constantly
people regularly update they do goget
dasu and they update their version
without caring they don't even look at
the semantic version because go has
destroyed the do go Community has
destroyed the relevance of the semantic
version because nobody body actually
uses it properly which I made a whole
video about so so they go ahead and they
they they they'd have to do a go get to
grab the new one without even checking
it and number two they'd have to build
and then they have to create a release
and deploy it right um and if they're
following regular software practices
that should not happen that really
shouldn't happen but it does all the
time so let's say that happens let's say
that you get you know your stuff gets
vulnerable
um and then and then you know it it the
lid blows off the whole thing everybody
finds out that your software now has a
vulnerability and that this thing has a
vulnerability now everybody's running
around with their chicken cut their head
cut off are we exposed did we build
recently do we have it and you find out
that you do okay now here's here's the
kicker so let's say the goyama project
for security reasons which is usually
code for oh my God we are so ashamed of
being a of having done this let's say
that they pull the entire
project down and you before you go
saying that this never happens it does
happen it definitely happens because
they're the the they they literally pull
the plug on the whole project they're
like we cannot we do not know where it
was vulnerable we don't know level of
exposure we have a lot of code to review
we're just going to we're just going to
turn the lights out on this thing
completely okay what happens to you as a
developer and your security audit team
when the security audit team comes to
you for your application and you ask him
if you're exposed you say well we did
definitely build with that version
right and then they say something like
well um we'll just build it with the
other version but now you can't you
can't why because the software that you
depended on is now
gone enter go mod vendor if you had used
go mod vendor as
designed and right before you did those
dependencies if you if your previous
version of the software your last build
that was good your snapshot if you had
snapshotted your your all your Vendor
dependencies by doing go mod vendor you
would have every you'd have a copy of
that software and all of its exact
dependencies at that point in time
snapshot in your code repository that's
what go mod vender does and all you have
to do is revert you just have to revert
to your last commit and rebuild and you
are guaranteed to be back at that level
not only that but now your security
Auditors your security Auditors have
something to look at if you don't have a
copy of the vulnerable software because
you didn't vendor the dependency code
the dependent code in your own project
and and they pull the plug and go go
yaml in this case pretending pulls the
plug you no longer have access to the
software to even judge what exactly the
vulnerability is for yourself or ever to
even know what it is and assuming they
bring the system back up and everything
they will probably have completely
change they'll have to they'll have to
change their G repos they'll have to
have figured out how to PR their trees
there's going to be all kinds of things
that they're going to have to do to that
project before they can bring it up
again because that vulnerability is
going to be there and we got they got to
make sure that they might even have to
rebase the whole entire
repo I mean who knows right the point is
go mod vendor reduces your exposure in
the spirit of
sbom because it is not only a list a
software build of materials it's
literally the software you have not only
do you have a software bill of materials
which you do in the if you go look at it
here let's go find a new one here if you
go look in the vendor directory under
vendor there's your software building
materials right there oops um okay so
there it is I mean it's not a very big
one right you have it tells you what
version it tells you what the
dependencies are that's your software
build materials right there it literally
tells you every dependency you have on
what version that that is in addition by
the way to the go do suum
file um which is also got the check sums
in it it's a similar thing but the the
txt file is a little bit easier to read
so that that list of materials there
that's in the the modules. txt file
helps it's already a software build of
materials it tells you exactly what
version you had what dependencies you
are and right next to it you know yeah
okay so it blows your repo right but it
also causes you to be able to build your
software much faster anybody who's had
so anybody who is this is another
advantage of of go mod that I should
probably do another video about but one
of the best advantages of having go mod
vendor done is you do go mod bander once
you wait for all that software to
download which takes a while and and
boom it's there anybody that's building
your project from that point on so let's
say you have people doing development
they do not have to wait around and mess
with their VPN and everything that it
takes to get it all there because you've
got it in you've already got the
software there so all they have to do is
clone the one repo so if you like if
you're if you be feeling the pull
towards a monor repo which you shouldn't
cuz go does not work with monor repos
you can twist its arm but it is not
designed to work with monor repos
because tagging tagging inversing so I I
don't want to get into that but you get
the same speed advantage of a mono repo
because all the software has been pulled
down and Bloated up your git repo right
it's software so it's relatively but you
know it's the same amount of time in
fact you be end up saving more time
doing it once for your project and then
having everybody just pull down the
relevant files then all of the test
files and everything and people put big
things in test you know test files St so
so so not only do you have the software
Bill materials right there that shows
you everything you've got but now when
when in our hypothetical case where they
pulled yaml the yaml project because of
security problems they got to really get
rid of them you still have a copy of the
software if you didn't have Gan vendor
if you hadn't done that consider what
you would have to
do how are you going to roll
back you can't you can't
rebuild I mean you short of like taking
in somebody's like active cash directory
and hoping they have that version cash
or hoping that somebody has cloned the
repo someplace else which by the way if
they did and they left it available with
the vulnerability in it they're probably
going to take airs down too if they're
not they're being irresponsible right
why would you why would you Fork the yo
project and have a vulnerable Fork of it
available even though the one with the
vulnerability has been taken down
because it's so dangerous I mean if you
happen to find one like that why the
hell would you bring that software into
your project because now you can't even
Trace whether your project has the the
vulnerability because it hasn't been
identified within the source
code the better way to do this is to
have one directory a vendor directory
that has all of the snapshotted
dependencies that and a software build
of materials in the form of modules. txt
that is what go mod vendor gives you it
makes you more compliant with the future
of at least in this case the American
cyber War division uh cyber security um
cyber defense you know their potential
requirements that are come and it makes
you just overall feel much happier
because you've now got all your stuff so
it goes without saying that as as far as
I'm concerned every single project I
ever make from now on is going to use go
mod vendor period I I do not intend in
fact I would I would go so far as to say
to say with the influence of of of um
private repo dependency builds which has
been hit which has hit us with things
like GitHub Enterprise Cloud which
forces every single uh re module to be
private it's based on the nature of how
inner Source repos are managed uh I I
would go so far as to say that go mod go
mod vendor very well and I don't know I
don't have enough time into this to
decide but it very well could be the new
standard uh for building any go project
no matter how big um because because of
the facility with the with the ease with
which you can download the software and
build it without having to wait around
for all those other things and secondly
um uh well you know that that's the main
that's those are the main things the the
downside of this is that um you know you
do get you you do get blo you do get blo
but the boat it's not it's about half as
much as the bloat as you probably expect
because it's just the effective files
and you know is the blo is the bloat
worth it based on the fact that no one
can remove any of that software from you
because it's now part of your project
that's the number one reason you should
vendor in the first place the second one
is ease ease of use and the third is
security uh and the you know having the
built-in build materials hopefully that
gives you something to Mo over I
appreciate um the person who suggested
that I look at this idea from the Cyber
Defense Agency um and it you can make
your own considerations but give it a
try and let me know what you think um
join us in the Discord put it in the
comments below you think I'm pull of it
let me know um you think that I missed
something let me know but as far as I'm
concerned I feel much better all around
U by using G mod vendor